Hi, I'm an engineer
مرحبا، أنا مهندس
and I make robots.
وصنعت روبوتات.
Now, of course you all know what a robot is, right?
الآن، بالطبع تعرفون ما هو الروبوت، صحيح؟
If you don't, you'd probably go to Google,
إذا لم تعرفوا، فعلى الارجح ابحثوا في جوجل،
and you'd ask Google what a robot is.
واسئلوا جوجل ما هو الروبوت.
So let's do that.
لذا هيا نقوم بذلك.
We'll go to Google and this is what we get.
سنبحث فى جوجل وهذا ما نحصل عليه.
Now, you can see here there are lots of different types of robots,
الآن، يمكنكم أن تروا هنا أنواعاً كثيرة ومختلفة من الروبوتات،
but they're predominantly humanoid in structure.
لكن في الغالب هي تشبه البشر من حيث البنية.
And they look pretty conventional
ومنظرهم عادي جداً
because they've got plastic, they've got metal,
لأنهم من البلاستيك ومن المعدن،
they've got motors and gears and so on.
مزودين بالمحركات والتروس وغير ذلك.
Some of them look quite friendly,
بعضهم يبدو لطيفاً،
and you could go up and you could hug them.
يمكننا الذهاب ومعانقتهم.
Some of them not so friendly,
وبعضم ليس لطيفاً،
they look like they're straight out of "Terminator,"
وبعضهم مدمر بلا تردد،
in fact they may well be straight out of "Terminator."
فى الحقيقة ربما يكونوا مدمرين مباشرة.
You can do lots of really cool things with these robots --
يمكنكم أن تفعلوا أموراً رائعة جداً بهذه الروبوتات--
you can do really exciting stuff.
يمكنكم أن تفعلوا أشياء مثيرة جداً.
But I'd like to look at different kinds of robots --
لكن أود أن أنظر إلى أنواع مختلفة من الروبوتات--
I want to make different kinds of robots.
أريد أن أصنع أنواع مختلفة من الروبوتات.
And I take inspiration from the things that don't look like us,
أخذت هذا الإلهام من الأشياء التي لا تشبهنا،
but look like these.
لكن تشبه أولئك.
So these are natural biological organisms
لذا هذه الكائنات الحية الطبيعية
and they do some really cool things that we can't,
ويستطيعون أن يفعلوا أموراً رائعة جداً لا نستطيع فعلها،
and current robots can't either.
ولا الروبوتات الحالية.
They do all sorts of great things like moving around on the floor;
يقومون بمختلف الأشياء العظيمة كالتحرك على الأرض،
they go into our gardens and they eat our crops;
ويذهبون إلى حدائقنا ويأكلوا محاصيلنا،
they climb trees;
ويتسلقون الأشجار،
they go in water, they come out of water;
ويدخلون الماء ويخرجون،
they trap insects and digest them.
ويصطادون الحشرات ويتخلصون منها.
So they do really interesting things.
لذلك يفعلون أموراً مهمة جداً.
They live, they breathe, they die,
يعيشون ويتنفسون ويموتون،
they eat things from the environment.
يأكلون أشياءً من البيئة.
Our current robots don't really do that.
الروبوتات التي لدينا حالياً لا تقوم بذلك حقا.
Now, wouldn't it be great
الآن، ألن يكون رائعاً
if you could use some of those characteristics in future robots
إذا استطعتم استخدام بعض من هذه السمات فى الروبوتات المستقبلية
so that you could solve some really interesting problems?
قفد تستطيعون حل بعض المشاكل المهمة جداً
I'm going to look at a couple of problems now in the environment
سأنظر في عدد من المشاكل الحالية فى البيئة
where we can use the skills and the technologies
حيث نستطيع استخدام المهارات والتكنولوجيات
derived from these animals
المستمدة من هذه الحيونات
and from the plants,
ومن النباتات،
and we can use them to solve those problems.
نستطيع استخدامهم لحل تلك المشاكل.
Let's have a look at two environmental problems.
دعونا نلقي نظرة على مشكلتين فى البيئة.
They're both of our making --
كلاهما من صنعنا--
this is man interacting with the environment
هذا رجل يتفاعل مع البيئة
and doing some rather unpleasant things.
ويفعل بعض الأمور المزعجة نوعاً ما
The first one is to do with the pressure of population.
أول شئ تفعله حيال الضغط السكاني.
Such is the pressure of population around the world
مثل الضغط السكاني حول العالم
that agriculture and farming is required to produce more and more crops.
أنه يتطلب من الزراعة إنتاج محاصيل أكثر وأكثر.
Now, to do that,
الآن، لفعل ذلك،
farmers put more and more chemicals onto the land.
يضع المزارعون الكيماويات أكثر فأكثر في الأرض.
They put on fertilizers, nitrates, pesticides --
يضعون الأسمدة والنترات والمبيدات الحشرية،
all sorts of things that encourage the growth of the crops,
مختلف الأشياء التي تزيد من نمو المحاصيل،
but there are some negative impacts.
لكن لها بعض التأثيرات السلبية.
One of the negative impacts is if you put lots of fertilizer on the land,
أحد هذه التأثيرات السلبية لو وضعت الكثير من الأسمدة في الأرض،
not all of it goes into the crops.
لا يذهب كلها إلى المحاصيل.
Lots of it stays in the soil,
الكثير منها يبقى في التربة،
and then when it rains,
وعندما تمطر،
these chemicals go into the water table.
تذهب هذه الكيماويات إلى المياه الجوفية.
And in the water table,
وفي المياه الجوفية،
then they go into streams, into lakes, into rivers
ثم تذهب الجداول وإلى البحيرات وإلى الأنهار،
and into the sea.
وإلى البحر.
Now, if you put all of these chemicals, these nitrates,
الآن، لو وضعت كل هذه الكيماويات وهذه النترات،
into those kinds of environments,
فى تلك الأنواع من البيئات،
there are organisms in those environments that will be affected by that --
هناك كائنات حية فى هذه البيئات ستتأثر بهذا--
algae, for example.
الطحلب على سبيل المثال.
Algae loves nitrates, it loves fertilizer,
يحب الطحلب النترات والسماد،
so it will take in all these chemicals,
ستأخذ كل هذه الكيماويات،
and if the conditions are right, it will mass produce.
ولو كانت الظروف ملائمة ستنتج بشكل واسع،
It will produce masses and masses of new algae.
ستنتج بشكل واسع طحلب جديد.
That's called a bloom.
هذا يسمى تفتّح.
The trouble is that when algae reproduces like this,
المشكلة حينما يعيد الطحلب الإنتاج بهذا الشكل،
it starves the water of oxygen.
يحرم الماء من الأكسجين.
As soon as you do that,
وبمجرد فعل هذا،
the other organisms in the water can't survive.
لا تستطيع الكائنات الحية الأخرى البقاء على قيد الحياة.
So, what do we do?
لذا، ماذا نفعل؟
We try to produce a robot that will eat the algae,
نحاول صنع روبوت سيأكل هذه الطحلب،
consume it and make it safe.
تستهلكه وتجعله آمناً.
So that's the first problem.
هذه أول مشكلة.
The second problem is also of our making,
المشكلة الثانية هي من صنع أيدينا،
and it's to do with oil pollution.
ويتعلق بالتلوث النفطي.
Now, oil comes out of the engines that we use,
الآن، يخرج النفط من المحركات التي نستخدمها،
the boats that we use.
والسفن التي نستخدمها.
Sometimes tankers flush their oil tanks into the sea,
أحيانا تتخلص ناقلات البترول من خزانات الوقود في البحر،
so oil is released into the sea that way.
لذا ينطلق النفط في البحر بهذه الطريقة.
Wouldn't it be nice if we could treat that in some way
ألن يكون جميلاً لو تعاملنا بطريقة ما
using robots that could eat the pollution the oil fields have produced?
باستخدام الروبوتات التى تلتهم التلوث من الحقول النفطية التي أُنتجت؟
So that's what we do.
لذلك هذا ما نقوم به.
We make robots that will eat pollution.
صنعنا الروبوتات التي تلتهم التلوث
To actually make the robot,
فى الحقيقة لصنع روبوت
we take inspiration from two organisms.
نأخذ الإلهام من اثنين من الكائنات الحية.
On the right there you see the basking shark.
والحق هنا أنك ترى القرش المتشمس.
The basking shark is a massive shark.
القرش المتشمس قرش ضخم.
It's noncarnivorous, so you can swim with it,
إنه لا يأكل اللحوم لذا تستطيعون السباحة معه،
as you can see.
كما ترون.
And the basking shark opens its mouth,
ويفتح القرش المتشمس فمه،
and it swims through the water, collecting plankton.
ويسبح في الماء يجمع العوالق.
As it does that, it digests the food,
كما يفعل ذلك فإنه يهضم الطعام،
and then it uses that energy in its body to keep moving.
فيستخدم هذه الطاقة فى جسده للحفاظ على حركته.
So, could we make a robot like that --
لذلك، نستطيع صنع روبوت هكذا--
like the basking shark that chugs through the water
كالقرش المتشمس الذي يحدث ضجة فى الماء
and eats up pollution?
ويلتهم التلوث؟
Well, let's see if we can do that.
حسنا،هيا نرى إن كنا نستطيع فعل هذا.
But also, we take the inspiration from other organisms.
لكن أيضا، أخذنا الإلهام من كائنات أخرى.
I've got a picture here of a water boatman,
قد حصلت على صورة هنا لحشرة مركب الماء،
and the water boatman is really cute.
وحشرة مركب الماء بارعة
When it's swimming in the water,
حينما تسبح فى البحر
it uses its paddle-like legs to push itself forward.
وتجدف بأرجلها لدفع نفسها للأمام.
So we take those two organisms
لذا نأخذ هاذين الكائنين
and we combine them together to make a new kind of robot.
ونمزجهم مع بعضهم لصنع نوع جديد من الروبوت
In fact, because we're using the water boatman as inspiration,
في الحقيقة، لأننا نستخدم حشرة مراكب الماء كإلهام،
and our robot sits on top of the water,
وهذا الربوت يجلس على سطح الماء،
and it rows,
ويجدف،
we call it the "Row-bot."
نسميه "الربوت المجدف".
So a Row-bot is a robot that rows.
لذا هو روبوت يجدف
OK. So what does it look like?
حسنا. إذا ماذا يشبه؟
Here's some pictures of the Row-bot,
هنا بعض الصور للروبوت المجدف،
and you'll see,
وستجدون كلكم،
it doesn't look anything like the robots we saw right at the beginning.
أنه لا يشبه في شيء الروبتات التى رأيناها هنا في البداية
Google is wrong; robots don't look like that,
جوجل مخطئ; فالروبوتات لا تشبه تلك،
they look like this.
إنها تشبه هذا
So I've got the Row-bot here.
لذا لدي روبوت مجدف هنا.
I'll just hold it up for you.
سأريكم إياه.
It gives you a sense of the scale,
يعطيكم إحساساً بالمقارنة
and it doesn't look anything like the others.
وإنه لا يشبه أي يء كالآخرين
OK, so it's made out of plastic,
حسنا، إنه مصنوع من البلاستيك،
and we'll have a look now at the components
وسنلقى نظرة على المكونات
that make up the Row-bot --
التى تُشكل الروبوت المجدف--
what makes it really special.
وما الذي يجعله استثنائياً.
The Row-bot is made up of three parts,
الروبوت المجدف مكون من ثلاث أجزاء،
and those three parts are really like the parts of any organism.
وهذه الثلاث أجزاء تشبه جداً أعضاء أي كائن حي
It's got a brain,
لديها مخ،
it's got a body
لديها جسد،
and it's got a stomach.
ولديها معدة،
It needs the stomach to create the energy.
تحتاج إلى المعدة لتولد طاقة.
Any Row-bot will have those three components,
أي ربوت مجدف سيكون لديه هذه المكونات الثلاث،
and any organism will have those three components,
وأي كائن حي سيكون لديه هذه المكونات
so let's go through them one at a time.
لذا هيا نبحث فيهم الواحد تلو الآخر.
It has a body,
لديه جسد،
and its body is made out of plastic,
جسدها مصنوع من البلاستيك،
and it sits on top of the water.
ويمكث على سطح الماء.
And it's got flippers on the side here --
ولديه زعنفة على الجانب هنا--
paddles that help it move,
مجادف يساعده على الحركة،
just like the water boatman.
كحشرة مركب الماء
It's got a plastic body,
له جسم من البلاستيك
but it's got a soft rubber mouth here,
لكن له فم مطامي أملس هنا،
and a mouth here -- it's got two mouths.
وفم هنا-- له فمّان.
Why does it have two mouths?
لم هو له فمّان؟
One is to let the food go in
واحد يسمح للطعام بالدخول
and the other is to let the food go out.
وواحد يسمح للطعام بالخروج.
So you can see really it's got a mouth and a derriere,
وبالتالى يمكنكم أن تروا حقا أن له فم ّ ومؤخرة،
or a --
أو-----
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
something where the stuff comes out,
شيئا حيث تخرج منه المواد،
which is just like a real organism.
الذى يشبه كائن حي حقيقى.
So it's starting to look like that basking shark.
وبالتالي أصبح يشبه ذلك القرش المتشمس.
So that's the body.
لذلك هذا هو الجسد.
The second component might be the stomach.
المكون الثاني ربما يكون المعدة.
We need to get the energy into the robot and we need to treat the pollution,
نحتاج لضخ الطاقة داخل الروبوت ونحتاج إلى التعامل مع التلوث،
so the pollution goes in,
وبالتالي يدخل التلوث،
and it will do something.
وسيفعل شيئاً.
It's got a cell in the middle here called a microbial fuel cell.
لديه خلية فى الوسط هنا تسمى بخلية وقود جرثومية.
I'll put this down, and I'll lift up the fuel cell.
سأضع هذا جانباً، وسأرفع خلية الوقود.
Here. So instead of having batteries,
هنا. بالتالي بدلا من البطاريات،
instead of having a conventional power system,
وبدلا من وضع نظام طاقة تقليدي،
it's got one of these.
يكون له واحد من هؤلاء .
This is its stomach.
هذه معدته.
And it really is a stomach
وإنها حقا معدة
because you can put energy in this side in the form of pollution,
لأنه يمكنك وضع طاقة في هذا الجانب فى هيئة التلوث،
and it creates electricity.
ويولد كهرباء.
So what is it?
وبالتالي ما هذا؟
It's called a microbial fuel cell.
إنها تسمى خلية الوقود الجرثومية.
It's a little bit like a chemical fuel cell,
إنها صغيرة كخلية وقود كميائية،
which you might have come across in school,
التى ربما مررتم عليها فى المدرسة،
or you might've seen in the news.
أو ربما رأيتموها فى الأخبار.
Chemical fuel cells take hydrogen and oxygen,
تأخذ خلايا الوقود الكميائية هيدروجين وأكسجين،
and they can combine them together and you get electricity.
وتمزجهم مع بعضهم ويمكنكم الحصول على كهرباء.
That's well-established technology; it was in the Apollo space missions.
وهذه تكنولوجيا معترف بها: كانت فى بعثات أبولو الفضائية.
That's from 40, 50 years ago.
وهذا من 40 إلى 50 سنة.
This is slightly newer.
هذه أحدث إلى حد ما.
This is a microbial fuel cell.
هذه خلية وقود جرثومية.
It's the same principle:
إنه نفس المبدأ:
it's got oxygen on one side,
تحصل على أوكسحين من جانب،
but instead of having hydrogen on the other,
لكن بدلا من جود هيدروجين من الجانب الآخر،
it's got some soup,
لديها بعض الحساء،
and inside that soup there are living microbes.
وبداخل ذلك الحساء ميكروبات حية.
Now, if you take some organic material --
الآن ، لو أخذت بعض المواد العضوية--
could be some waste products, some food,
قد تكون بعض المخلفات وبعض الطعام
maybe a bit of your sandwich --
وربما تكون جزء من ساندويتش لك--
you put it in there, the microbes will eat that food,
وضعته هناك، وستأكل ،الميكروبات ذلك الطعام
and they will turn it into electricity.
وستحوله إلى كهرباء.
Not only that, but if you select the right kind of microbes,
ليس هذا فقط، لكن إذا اخترتم النوع المناسب من الميكروبات،
you can use the microbial fuel cell to treat some of the pollution.
تستطيعون استخدام خلية الوقود الجرثومية للتعامل مع بعض التلوث.
If you choose the right microbes,
لو اخترتم الميكروبات المناسبة،
the microbes will eat the algae.
ستأكل الميكروبات الطحلب.
If you use other kinds of microbes,
لو استخدمتم نوعاً أخر من الميكروبات،
they will eat petroleum spirits and crude oil.
ستأكل حيوية البترول والبترول الخام.
So you can see how this stomach could be used
يمكنكم أن تروا كيف يمكن استخدام هذه المعدة
to not only treat the pollution
ليس فقط للتعامل مع التلوث
but also to generate electricity from the pollution.
لكن أيضا لتوليد كهرباء من التلوث.
So the robot will move through the environment,
وبالتالي سيتحرك الروبوت فى البيئة
taking food into its stomach,
يأخذ الطعام إلى معدته،
digest the food, create electricity,
ويهضم الطعام ويولد الكهرباء،
use that electricity to move through the environment
ويستخدم تلك الكهرباء للتحرك في البيئة
and keep doing this.
ويستمر في فعل هذا.
OK, so let's see what happens when we run the Row-bot --
حسنا، دعونا نرى ما يحدث حينما نشغل الروبوت المجدف--
when it does some rowing.
حينما يقوم ببعض التجديف.
Here we've got a couple of videos,
لدينا هنا فيديوهات عديدة،
the first thing you'll see -- hopefully you can see here
أول شئ سترونه-- آمل أن تستطيعوا رؤيته هنا
is the mouth open.
الفم وهو يفتح.
The front mouth and the bottom mouth open,
الفم الأمامي والفم السفلي يفتح،
and it will stay opened enough,
وسيبقى مفتوحاً ما يكفي،
then the robot will start to row forward.
ثم سيبدأ الروبوت بالتجديف للأمام.
It moves through the water
يتحرك في الماء
so that food goes in as the waste products go out.
كي يدخل الطعام كما تخرج المخلفات.
Once it's moved enough,
ما إن يتحرك كفاية،
it stops and then it closes the mouth --
يتوقف ثم يغلق فمه--
slowly closes the mouths --
يغلق فمه ببطء،
and then it will sit there,
وثم يجلس هناك،
and it will digest the food.
وسيهضم الطعام.
Of course these microbial fuel cells,
بالطبع خلايا الوقود الميكروية تلك،
they contain microbes.
تحتوى على ميكروبات.
What you really want is lots of energy
ما تريدونه حقاً الكثير من الطاقة
coming out of those microbes as quickly as possible.
تخرج من هذه المكيروبات أسرع قدر الإمكان.
But we can't force the microbes
لكن لا نستطيع إجبار الميكروبات
and they generate a small amount of electricity per second.
ويولدون مقداراً قليلاً من الكهرباء في الثانية.
They generate milliwatts, or microwatts.
يولدون ميلي وات أو ميكر وات.
Let's put that into context.
دعونا نضع هذا في الحسبان.
Your mobile phone for example,
هواتفكم على سبيل المثال،
one of these modern ones,
أحد تلك الأشياء الحديثة،
if you use it, it takes about one watt.
لو استخدمتوها تـأخذ حوالي واحد وات.
So that's a thousand or a million times as much energy that that uses
حتى ألف أو مليون مرة أكثر من الطاقة التى تستخدم
compared to the microbial fuel cell.
مقارنة بخلية الوقود الميكروبية.
How can we cope with that?
كيف نتعامل مع ذلك؟
Well, when the Row-bot has done its digestion,
حسنا، عندما ينتهي الربوت المجدف من هضمه،
when it's taken the food in,
عندما يأخذ الطعام إلى الداخل،
it will sit there and it will wait until it has consumed all that food.
سيجلس هناك وينتظر حتى يستهلك كل ذلك الطعام.
That could take some hours, it could take some days.
وهذا قد يأخذ بضع ساعات، وبضع أيام.
A typical cycle for the Row-bot looks like this:
دوره مثالية للربوت المجدف تشبه هذا
you open your mouth,
تفتح فمك ،
you move,
تتحرك،
you close your mouth
تغلق فمك
and you sit there for a while waiting.
وتجلس هناك بينما تنتظر.
Once you digest your food,
إلى أن تهضم طعامك،
then you can go about doing the same thing again.
ثم تمضي فى فعل الشيء نفسه مرة أخرى.
But you know what, that looks like a real organism, doesn't it?
لكن تعرفون ماذا، ذلك يشبه كائن حي حقيقى أليس كذلك؟
It looks like the kind of thing we do.
يشبه الشيء الذي نقوم به.
Saturday night, we go out, open our mouths,
ليلة السبت، نخرج، ونفتح أفواهنا
fill our stomachs,
ونملئ بطوننا،
sit in front of the telly and digest.
ونجلس أمام التليفزيون ونهضم الطعام.
When we've had enough, we do the same thing again.
عندما كان لدينا ما يكفى، فعلنا نفس الشيء مرة أخرى.
OK, if we're lucky with this cycle,
حسنا، لو أننا محظوظون بهذه الدورة،
at the end of the cycle we'll have enough energy left over
فى نهاية الدورة سيكون لدينا ما يكفى من الطاقة المتبقية
for us to be able to do something else.
لنا لنكون قادرين على فعل شيء أخر.
We could send a message, for example.
نستطيع إرسال رسالة، على سبيل المثال
We could send a message saying,
نستطيع إرسال رسالة مفادها،
"This is how much pollution I've eaten recently,"
"هذا هو مقدار التلوث التي أكلته حاليا"،
or, "This is the kind of stuff that I've encountered,"
أو"هذا نوع من الأشياء التي واجهتها"،
or, "This is where I am."
أو" هذا ما فعلته".
That ability to send a message saying, "This is where I am,"
هذه القدرة على إرسال رسالة تقول ، " هذا ما فعلته"،
is really, really important.
هي حقاً فى غاية الأهمية.
If you think about the oil slicks that we saw before,
لو فكرتم في البقعة النفطية التى رأيناها من قبل،
or those massive algal blooms,
أو أولئك الطحالب المزهرة،
what you really want to do is put your Row-bot out there,
ما تريدون فعله حقاً هو نشر الروبوت المجدف الخاص بكم هناك،
and it eats up all of those pollutions,
ويلتهم كل ذلك التلوث،
and then you have to go collect them.
ثم تذهبون لجمعهم
Why?
لماذا؟
Because these Row-bots at the moment,
لأن تلك الروبوتات المجدفة حالياً،
this Row-bot I've got here,
هذا الروبوت الذي أحضرته هنا،
it contains motors, it contains wires,
يحتوي على محركات وأسلاك،
it contains components which themselves are not biodegradable.
ويحتوي على أجزاء غير قابلة للتحلل.
Current Row-bots contain things like toxic batteries.
الروبوتات المجدفة حالياً بها أشياء كالبطاريات السامة.
You can't leave those in the environment,
فلا تستطيعون ترك تلك الأشياء في البيئة،
so you need to track them,
لذلك تحتاجون تعقبهم،
and then when they've finished their job of work,
وعندما ينتهون من عملهم،
you need to collect them.
تحتاجون لجمعهم.
That limits the number of Row-bots you can use.
هذا يحصر عدد الروبوتات المجدفة التي تستخدمونها.
If, on the other hand,
على الجانب الآخر، لو
you have robot a little bit like a biological organism,
أن لديكم روبوتاً صغيراً ككائن حي جرثومي،
when it comes to the end of its life,
عندما تحين نهاية حياته،
it dies and it degrades to nothing.
يموت ويصبح لا شيء يُذكر
So wouldn't it be nice if these robots,
لذا ألن يكون رائعاً لو أن هذه الروبوتات،
instead of being like this, made out of plastic,
بدلا من أن تكون مثل هذا , فهي صنعت من البلاستيك
were made out of other materials,
وصُنعت من مواد أخرى،
which when you throw them out there,
حينما ترميهم هناك،
they biodegrade to nothing?
يتحللون إلى لا شيء
That changes the way in which we use robots.
هذا يغير الطريقة التى نستخدمها مع الروبوتات.
Instead of putting 10 or 100 out into the environment,
بدلا من نشر 10 إلى 100 فى البئية،
having to track them,
نضطر إلى تتبعهم،
and then when they die,
ثم حينما يموتون،
collect them,
نجمعهم،
you could put a thousand,
يمكنكم أن تضعوا ألفاً،
a million, a billion robots into the environment.
أو مليوناً أو بليوناً من الروبوتات فى البيئة.
Just spread them around.
فقط انشروهم في الأرجاء.
You know that at the end of their lives, they're going to degrade to nothing.
تعرفون أنهم في نهاية حياتهم يصبحون لا شيء.
You don't need to worry about them.
لا تحتاجون القلق بشأنهم.
So that changes the way in which you think about robots
حتى تغير الطريقة التي تفكر بها حول الروبوتات
and the way you deploy them.
وطريقة نشرك لهم.
Then the question is: Can you do this?
فالسؤال هو : هل تستطيع فعل هذا؟
Well, yes, we have shown that you can do this.
حسنا، نعم، أثبتنا أنه يمكنكم فعل هذا.
You can make robots which are biodegradable.
يمكنكم صنع روبوتات غير قابلة للتحلل.
What's really interesting is you can use household materials
الأمر المثير حقاً أنه يمكنكم استخدام مواد منزلية
to make these biodegradable robots.
لصنع هذه الروبوتات التي لا تحلل.
I'll show you some; you might be surprised.
سأعرض لكم بعض الأشياء; ربما تدهشون.
You can make a robot out of jelly.
يمكنكم صنع روبوت من الهلام.
Instead of having a motor, which we have at the moment,
بدلاً من وجود محرك كالذي بحوزتنا الآن،
you can make things called artificial muscles.
يمكنكم صُنع أشياء تُسمى عضلات اصطناعية.
Artificial muscles are smart materials,
العضلات الاصطناعية مواد ذكية،
you apply electricity to them,
توصلون الكهرباء بهم،
and they contract, or they bend or they twist.
ويقبضون العضلات أو ينحنون أويلتون.
They look like real muscles.
يشبهون العضلات الحقيقية.
So instead of having a motor, you have these artificial muscles.
وبالتالي بدلا من وجود محرك يكون بحوزتكم هذه العضلات الاصطناعية.
And you can make artificial muscles out of jelly.
وتصنعون عضلات اصطناعية من الهلام.
If you take some jelly and some salts,
لو أخذتم بعض من الهلام وبعض من الملح،
and do a bit of jiggery-pokery,
وقمتم بقليل من الخدع،
you can make an artificial muscle.
تستطيعون صُنع عضلة اصطناعية.
We've also shown you can make the microbial fuel cell's stomach
أثبتنا لكم أنه بإمكانكم صنع معدة خلية وقود ميكروبية
out of paper.
من الورق.
So you could make the whole robot out of biodegradable materials.
وبالتالي بإمكانكم صُنع ربوت من مواد غير قابلة للتحلل.
You throw them out there, and they degrade to nothing.
تقومون برميهم هناك ويصبحون لا شيء.
Well, this is really, really exciting.
حسنا،هذا حقاً مثيرٌ جداً.
It's going to totally change the way in which we think about robots,
سوف يغير بالكلية الطريقة التي نفكر بها حول الروبوتات،
but also it allows you to be really creative
لكن يسمح لكم أيضاً لتكونوا مبدعين حقاً
in the way in which you think about what you can do with these robots.
في الطريقة التى تفكرون بها عن ما يمكنكم فعله بهذه الروبوتات.
I'll give you an example.
سأعطيكم مثالاً.
If you can use jelly to make a robot --
لو استطعتم استخدام هلام لصنع روبوت--
now, we eat jelly, right?
الآن، نحن نأكل الهلام،صحيح؟
So, why not make something like this?
وبالتالي، لما لا نصنع شيئا كهذا؟
A robot gummy bear.
روبوت حلوى الدب اللزجة.
Here, I've got some I prepared earlier.
هنا، لدي بعض منهم أعددتهم مسبقاً.
There we go. I've got a packet --
ها نحن ذا. لدي عبوة--
and I've got a lemon-flavored one.
وبنكهة الليمون.
I'll take this gummy bear -- he's not robotic, OK?
سأخذ هذه حلوى الدب هذه-- هو ليس روبوتاً، حسناً؟
We have to pretend.
علينا أن نزعم.
And what you do with one of these is you put it in your mouth --
وما يمكنكم فعله بواحدة من هذه إذا وضعتوها في أفواهكم--
the lemon's quite nice.
الليمون لذيذ نوعاً ما.
Try not to chew it too much, it's a robot, it may not like it.
حاولوا ألا تمضغوها كثيراً، إنها روبوت، ربما لا تحبوها.
And then you swallow it.
ثم قوموا بابتلاعها.
And then it goes into your stomach.
فستذهب إلى معدتكم.
And when it's inside your stomach, it moves, it thinks, it twists, it bends,
وعندما تكون بداخل معدتكم، تتحرك وتفكر وتلتوي وتنحني،
it does something.
إنها تفعل شيئا.
It could go further down into your intestines,
تدخل إلى أمعاءكم،
find out whether you've got some ulcer or cancer,
تكتشف إذا ما كان عندكم قرحة أو سرطان،
maybe do an injection, something like that.
ربما القيام بالحقن كهذا.
You know that once it's done its job of work,
تعرفون إنها فقط تقوم بعملها،
it could be consumed by your stomach,
يمكن أن تستهلكها معدتكم،
or if you don't want that,
أو إن كنتم لا تريدون ذلك،
it could go straight through you,
فيمكن أن تذهب مباشرة منكم،
into the toilet,
إلى الحمام،
and be degraded safely in the environment.
وتصبح لا شيء في البيئة.
So this changes the way, again, in which we think about robots.
وبالتالي هذا يغير مرة أخرى الطريقة التي تفكرون بها حول الروبوتات
So, we started off looking at robots that would eat pollution,
لذا بدأنا نتجه إلى الروبوتات التي تأكل التلوث،
and then we're looking at robots which we can eat.
وننظر إلى الربوتات التي نأكلها.
I hope this gives you some idea
آمل أن يعطيكم هذا بعض الأفكار
of the kinds of things we can do with future robots.
ببعض الأشياء التى يمكن فعلها بالروبوتات المستقبلية.
Thank you very much for your attention.
شكراً جزيلاً لكم على انتباهكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)